[ foghorn blasts ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ distant foghorn blast ]
[ foghorn continues ]
[ waves crashing ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ foghorn blasting loudly ]
[ foghorn continues ]
[ waves crashing ]
[ clock ticking ]
[ wind howling outside ]
[ match strikes ]
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ rattling ]
[ stairs creaking ]
- [ thud ] - Ow .
[ water trickling ]
[ Thomas farts ]
[ whistling ]
[ farts ]
[ continues whistling ]
[ clock ticking ]
[ wind howling ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ whirring and clanking ]
[ foghorn blasts ]
[ foghorn continues ]
[ wind howling ]
[ Thomas exhales ]
Should pale death with treble dread
make the ocean caves our bed ,
God who hear 'st the surges roll ,
deign to save our suppliant soul .
To four weeks !
No , sir . Thank you .
It 's bad luck to leave a toast unfinished , lad .
Oh , meanin ' ... Meanin ' no disrespect .
Man what don 't drink , best have his reasons .
Uh ... Ain 't it ...
I ... I understood it 's against regulations , sir .
Did you ?
I did , sir . From , uh ... From them 's manual .
Didn 't picture you a readin ' man .
[ snickers ]
Well , I ain 't trying for trouble .
Then you 'll do as I say .
That 's in yer book too .
[ grunts ]
To four weeks .
[ cups clank ]
- [ sputtering ] - [ laughing ]
[ coughing ]
Aye . Aye . The cistern needs a-lookin ' to .
One of yer duties , lad .
Or didn 't y 'read yerself about it ?
You 'll clean the brass and the clockwork ,
and you 'll tidy up the quarters after .
And there 's well more to be mended outside .
D 'y 'hear me , lad ?
[ sighs ] Yes , sir .
Aye , sir !
[ scoffs ] Aye , sir .
[ snorts ]
When the fog clears ,
you 'll work through the dog watch .
Doggin ' it ? I was ' specting I 'd git up to see the lantern .
I tend the light .
Well , the rules is alternatin ' shifts .
It 's the mid watch that 's to dread , lad .
My watch , night to morning .
Some new junior man I 'm fixed with .
See to yer duties . The light is mine .
[ foghorn blaring ]
[ machinery whirring and clanking ]
[ foghorn blasts loudly ]
Son of a bitch !
[ foghorn blasts ]
[ metallic clinking ]
[ mechanical ticking and clicking ]
To ye , me beauty .
[ high-pitched screeching ]
[ mermaid screeches ]
[ Thomas ] Shingles .
Tend to ' em after the cistern .
And the lamp , she needs oil .
[ shoes clatter ]
Aye , sir .
[ Thomas exhales and farts ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ grunting softly ]
[ coughing ]
[ sludge sloshing ]
[ wind howling ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ grunting ]
[ squawking ]
[ squawking loudly ]
- [ rattles ] - Go !
Move it .
[ squawking ]
[ squawking furiously ]
- [ thudding ] - [ panting ]
[ grunts ]
[ continues panting ]
[ grunting and panting ]
[ panting heavily ]
You don 't go in there !
- Oil , sir . - Tired ? Use this next time .
Save you a helluva lot of trouble .
Catch yer breath , lad .
I said , catch yer breath , lad .
[ inhales sharply ]
Then bring that drum
back down the ladderwell where y 'found it .
' Less ye 're fixin ' to burn the whole light down .
Then see to the rest of yer duties .
Ye 're behindhand already .
- Aye , sir . - Ye 're too slow . You a dullard ?
No , sir .
Fooled me .
[ clangs ]
[ lock clicking ]
[ grunts ]
Should pale death with treble dread
make the ocean caves our bed ,
God who hear 'st the surges roll ,
deign to save the suppliant soul .
[ cups clank ]
Still tastes o 'the head ?
Ah , find some chirk in ye , lad .
Now is the time for gab and chatter .
Y 'best be enjoying it .
Come a fortnight and the brace of us 'll be wantin '
to be ever silent as the tomb .
I ain 't much for talkin ' .
Reckon ye 're the first ?
No , sir . I don 't .
Y 'ain 't .
The Chicopee , a fine-un she were .
Clean-built and trig-lookin ' !
None more fleet in ' 64 than she .
We were on the breaks ...
A mutiny , it were ...
And why , ask ye ? Why ?
What 's the terrible part of a sailor 's life , ask ye , lad ?
' Tis when the work stops when ye 're twixt wind and water .
Doldrums . Doldrums .
Eviler than the Devil .
Boredom makes men to villains ,
and the water goes quick , lad , vanished .
The only med 'cine is drink .
Keeps them sailors happy , keeps ' em agreeable ,
keeps ' em calm , keeps ' em ...
Stupid .
[ laughing ]
Curse me if there ain 't an old tar spirit
somewheres in ye , lad .
[ exhales and pours drink ]
Out with it , lad .
Uh ...
What , uh ... What made your last keeper leave ?
Him ? Me second ?
Mmm-hmm .
Died .
Went mad , he did .
Ravin ' about sirens , merfolk , bad omens and the like .
In the end ,
weren 't no more sense left in him than an hen 's tooth .
He believed that there was some enchantment in the light .
He notioned that St. Elmo
had cast his very fire into it .
Salvation , said he .
[ scoffs ]
[ chuckles ]
Tall tales .
I seen ye sparrin ' with a gull .
Best leave ' em be .
Bad luck to kill a sea bird .
[ scoffs ]
More tall tales .
Bad luck to kill a sea bird !
Pay me no mind , lad .
None .
Fix us up some coffee .
Long night ahead .
Drop o 'coffee will do us good .
[ clock ticking ]
[ wind howling outside ]
[ tapping ]
[ grunts softly ]
[ soft thumping ]
[ grunts ]
[ door creaks ]
[ waves crashing ]
- [ seagulls squawking ] - [ grunting ]
[ blows ]
You 've been neglecting yer duties , lad !
Don 't deny it !
What do you call that ?
- Sir ? - What ?
I ... I mopped and swept twice over , sir .
Ye lyin ' dog .
- I swept ' em . - ' Tis begrimed and bedabbled .
Unwiped , unwashed , and distained .
[ chuckles softly ]
You git some kinda peart outta molestin ' me ?
Come now ?
I already said ...
How dare ye contradict me , y 'dog .
Now look here ,
I ain 't never intended to be no housewife
nor slave in takin ' this job .
It ain 't right !
These lodgings is more ramshackle
than any shanty boy 's camp I ever seen .
The Queen of England 's own fancy housekeeper
couldn 't even done no better than what I done ,
' cause I tell you , I scrubbed
this here place twice over , sir ...
And I say y 'did nothin ' o 'the sort .
And I say , y 'swab it again ,
and y 'swab it proper-like this time ,
and you 'll be swabbin ' it 10 times more after that .
And if I tells ye to pull up and apart
every floorboard and clapboard of this here house
and scour ' em down with yer bare ,
bleedin ' knuckles , you 'll do it !
And if I tells ye to yank out every single nail
from every moulderin ' nail-hole
and suck off every spec of rust
till all them nails sparkle like a sperm whale 's pecker ,
and then carpenter the whole light station
back together from scrap ,
and then do it all over again , you 'll do it !
And by God and by Golly ,
you 'll do it smilin ' , lad , ' cause you 'll like it .
You 'll like it ' cause I says you will !
Contradict me again , and I 'll dock yer wages .
D 'ye hear me , lad ?
Aye , sir .
Ah .
Swab , dog .
Swab !
[ thunder rumbling ]
[ thunder rumbles ]
[ foghorn blasting ]
Keep ' em steady , lad .
Aye , sir . [ grunts ]
[ Thomas ] Whitewash must be even , lad .
Bright ! Shinin ' !
Like a silver whorehouse token .
Give them sailors a proper daymark .
[ Ephraim ] They 're not going to see it in a goddamn storm !
Keep your temper now , lad .
' Tis fine work .
And ye 're makin ' high marks in me logbook .
Them 's gospel !
I 'll drop y 'down a few feet .
- [ creaking ] - [ grunts ]
Easy !
Never been in better hands .
Quit yer flailing , lad .
- I ain 't ! - Y 'are !
- Keep still ! - I am !
[ screams ]
[ waves lapping ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
- [ seagull squawks ] - [ shooing ]
Git ! Git ! Git ! Git !
[ squawking ]
[ pen scratching on paper ]
Thank ye , lad .
Winslow .
Ephraim Winslow .
These last two weeks , I 'd ...
I 'd like it if you 'd call me by my name .
[ chuckling ] Listen to ye ,
giving orders , lad .
- Winslow . - All right , all right .
Suits me just as fine , Ephraim Winslow .
So , what brung such a one as ye to this damned rock ?
Such as what ?
Pretty as a picture .
[ laughing ] Only joshing , lad , only josh ...
- Winslow . - Winslow .
What brung ye ...
[ inhaling and exhaling ]
... to this rock , Ephraim Winslow ?
What were yer work afore ?
- Timber . - Timber ?
Big timber . Up north . Canada ways .
- Hudson Bay outfit ? - The same .
True what they say ?
" Forest as far as the eye can see " ?
Yessir . Spruce , tamarack , white pine .
" Bush , " them folk up there call it .
Had enough of trees , that it , then ?
Yes , sir .
Can 't say I blame ye .
I hearn tell about that life .
Hard goin ' .
Workin ' one man harder than two hosses , they say .
No thankee .
The sea , she 's the only situation wantin ' fer me .
Miss it ?
Ain 't nothing what can touch it .
But I can 't ... [ tapping leg ]
be draggin ' me old stump about .
Nay . Not worth the trouble ...
Now I 'm a wickie and a wickie I is .
And I 'm damn-well wedded to this here light ,
and she 's been a finer , truer , quieter wife
than any alive-blooded woman .
Y 'ever married ?
Thirteen Christmases at sea ...
Little ' uns at home .
She never forgave it .
' Tis fer the better .
Since we 're getting too friendly , Ephraim Winslow ,
tell me , what 's a timber man want with being a wickie ?
Not enough quiet for ye up north ?
Sawdust itching yer nethers ?
Foreman found ye too high-tempered
for carrying an axe ?
Like you said , I just had enough of trees , I guess .
Since I left Dad ,
I done every kind of work that can pay a man .
Some I ain 't near proud of .
- Drifter , eh ? - No , just ...
Can 't find a post I can take a real shine to ,
so I keep movin ' along .
And I ain 't the kind to look back
- at what 's behind him , see . - On the run ?
Now look here ,
ain 't nothin ' wrong with a man startin ' fresh , startin ' new ,
just lookin ' to earn a living ...
- No ... - [ sighs ]
Just like any man ,
just wanna settle down quiet-like with some earnings .
I read someplace that
a man could earn 630 ...
I read $ 1,000 a year
if he tends a light far off shore .
The further away , the more he earns .
I read that , and hell , I says , work .
Save my earnings .
Sometime soon I 'll raise my own roof ,
somewheres up country ,
with no one to tell me " what for " .
And that 's all .
Same old , borin ' story , eh ?
Well , you asked .
Say , why is it bad luck to kill a gull ?
In ' em 's the souls of sailors what met their maker .
You a prayin ' man , Winslow ?
Not as often as I might .
But I 'm God-fearin ' , if that 's what you 're askin ' .
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ panting ]
[ creaking ]
[ Ephraim sighs ]
[ groans exasperatedly ]
Shit .
[ whirring and clanking ]
[ Thomas babbling in distance ]
[ Thomas moaning ]
[ continues babbling ]
[ continues moaning ]
[ squelching ]
[ faint chittering ]
- [ stairs creaking ] - [ footsteps thudding ]
[ seagull screeches ]
[ screeching continues ]
[ screeching ]
[ squawking ]
- [ screeching ] - [ grunting ]
[ grunting ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
- [ squawking continues ] - [ panting ]
[ wind howling ]
[ footsteps approaching ]
Wind 's changed .
- Oh . Good riddance . - Oh , don 't be so darn foolish .
It 's the calm afore the storm , Winslow .
She were a gentle westerly wind ye 're cursin ' .
Only feels roughly
' cause you don 't know nothin ' about nothin ' ,
and there ain 't no trees on this here rock
like your Hudson Bay bush .
[ sighs ] Nor 'Easterly wind 'll come soon
ablowin ' like Gabriel 's horn .
Best board up them signal house winders .
Aye , sir .
' Twill keep steady afore the tender
comes in the morn , I ' spect ...
but there 's dirty weather knockin ' about .
Somethin ' stirring in ye ?
Ye 're gettin ' off this rock tomorry . Winslow .
Don 't start grudgen me now .
No , sir .
Keeping secrets , are ye ?
I could just use a hand with them boards , is all .
- [ hammering ] - [ foghorn blasting ]
Pull , Winslow !
Look at ' em !
Better than fin fishin ' !
Ain 't no crime to take a snort now .
A clear night . And our last afore relief .
I ain 't never know 'd an inspector
what wouldn 't turn a blind eye .
And I won 't take no for an answer .
[ snickers ]
Should pale death and treble dread ...
[ exhales ] Ah , hell ! To ... To relief !
- [ cups clank ] - And how !
Oh ! [ clears throat ]
[ sniffs ]
[ grunts ]
[ clears throat ]
[ both ] ♪ Hurrah , we 're homeward bound ♪
♪ Hurrah , we 're homeward bound ! ♪
[ Thomas ] ♪ When we 're arrived at Bedford docks ♪
♪ Them bloomers comin ' out in flocks ♪
♪ Them pretty girls They all did say ♪
♪ Here comes Jack with his nine-month pay ♪
[ both ] ♪ Hurrah , we 're homeward bound ♪
♪ Hurrah , we 're homeward bound ! ♪
... and a pretty lass , she were ,
takin ' off her bonnet ,
but as I says , I 'd broke me leg ,
and banged myself all up .
It was to a nuns ' hospital ...
All of them nuns were Catholics , I tell ye .
[ both laughing ]
But I never went to Salem since
without hoping that I should see her ,
for beddin ' down wer 'nt the same since .
You feel shame when you lie with a woman ?
I ain 't ' shamed of nothing !
[ both laughing ]
[ coughing ]
Well , I 'll say it ...
I might even miss ye , Ephraim Winslow .
- [ chuckles ] - Ye 're fastly a true blue wickie
in the making , you is .
Thought one night you was bound to
split me skull in twain ,
but ye 're a good-un .
Why , you 'll be workin ' the lamp in no time .
Why haven 't I ?
What ?
The light .
- [ chuckles ] - I 'm the keeper of this station , lad .
Some other station , y 'can tend the light .
The manual says ...
My log is the only book on this rock ...
[ both arguing ]
I 'm the keeper of the light , lad ,
I never let no man touch her ...
Don 't concern yerself with the beacon , lad !
Mine !
[ sighs ]
- [ laughing ] - [ chuckling ]
[ exhales ] Have it your way .
[ Thomas groans ]
- [ spits ] - [ cork clatters ]
Say , I never ...
I don 't ... I don 't know your name .
Wake .
Your Christian name .
Thomas .
- Thomas ? - Aye , Thomas Wake .
Call me Tom .
Well ...
To my friend Tom .
[ cups clank ]
And to gittin ' off this goddamned rock !
[ seagull squawking ]
[ clock ticking ]
[ Thomas snoring ]
[ groaning ]
[ clattering ]
[ wind howling ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ waves crashing ]
[ screams ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ screeching ]
[ continues screeching ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ inaudible ]
[ Thomas ] What 'r y 'splittin ' yer lungs fer ?
- [ panting ] - You smell o ' shit .
Best swab this mess afore the tender comes .
Do as ye 're told , lad ! The quarters are dire .
Aye ... Aye , sir .
Aye .
[ wind howling ]
[ foghorn blasts ]
- [ thunder cracks ] - [ distant foghorn ]
[ clock ticking ]
They didn 't come .
[ thunder cracking ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ machinery whirring and clanking ]
The damp 's got to the provisions !
What ?
[ foghorn blaring ]
The damp 's got to the foodstuffs .
The salt cod is out .
- Out ? - Blasted .
Gone to rot .
- Praised be . - Will you hear me now ?
- Hear what ? - That we best be rationing .
- Rationing ? - You insubordinate again ?
It 's only been one day .
Devil 's tail .
Look , maybe the tender did come .
We just missed her , is all .
I can take the dory out .
Weeks , Winslow . Weeks .
What ?
What do you mean , what ?
- Weeks ? - Weeks . Aye , weeks .
We slept in . Dead drunk .
It 's been weeks ago since we missed her , Winslow .
And I 've been askin ' ye to ration fer weeks now , too ,
but you 've kept barking at me like a mad dog
sayin ' you can " take the dory out . "
- Now , look here . - Oh , no .
Don 't be losing yer head now .
- This ain 't funny . - No , it ain 't .
And I ain 't want to be stranded here
with some damn lunatic .
[ chuckles ] Stranded ?
- That 's what I said . - [ distant foghorn ]
Why , I thought ... I thought you said relief was coming .
If we can wait out the storm .
[ stammers ] The tender is coming !
In ' 75 ,
Ol ' Striker were marooned here for seven long months , he was .
The storm died on the mainland ,
but here , the waters were too rageful
neither to launch nor land .
You 're just tryin ' to scare me .
Look at ye . Pretendin ' .
But ye well know yer lot .
[ thunder rumbling ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ wind blowing ]
[ Thomas ] Dig !
[ thunder rumbles ]
Dig , says I !
Dig !
There she lies .
Rations .
The worst of us couldn 't fend ' gainst the ship rats
what gnawed on the soles of our feet .
[ distant foghorn ]
Their legs withered and turned gangree 'nous ,
every shade of the peacock 's tail .
Their gums grew swollen ,
the color of bone , then to rot .
Tarry blood oozed ,
teeth droppin ' to the deck with none to hold on to .
" Land ho ! " hears I ,
but only grass on that island .
So we et upon the grass .
' And ' twas that scurvy
what left me locked ever since .
I thought you said you 'd broke it .
Aye ?
Your leg .
Catholic nuns and such like .
You must 've misheard .
- I told that dumb bastard ... - Yep .
Them eaves be gonners .
" Give me your cant hook , " I says to him .
But ... [ chuckles ] Foreman Winslow ,
that goddamned Canady bastard ...
- Winslow ? - ... always callin ' me a dog .
A filthy dog .
- I 'll show you who 's a dog . - Winslow .
- What about ... - Who , Winslow ?
The eaves be fallin ' ...
- He 's always raggin ' on me ... - Ragging ?
Like you .
Damn fool nonsense .
That 's the trouble with ye , Winslow .
Trouble with you is eatin ' grass without no teeth .
Come now ?
Your sea matey 's teeth had falled out .
What are ye gettin ' at , Winslow ?
Well , it just seems powerful hard
to eat grass with no teeth .
' Cause goats and sheeps and cows ...
Well , now , they all got teeth , don 't they ?
Y 'know how y 'eat grass without yer teeth ?
Oblige me .
Ye rip it out and ye swallow it .
[ both laughing ]
You rip it out and you swallow it .
- Ye rip it out ... - I don 't know ' bout that .
Y 'don 't ?
I don 't .
[ distant foghorn ]
[ window rattles ]
[ wood creaking ]
What ?
- What ? - What ?
[ both repeatedly ] What ?
- That 's what I mean ! - What ?
- That 's the trouble with you . - That 's the trouble with ye !
- With you ! - With ye !
No !
[ shouting ] No !
I want a steak !
I want a goddamned steak !
- [ laughing ] - I ...
If I had a steak ... Oh , boy !
A ... A rare , a bloody steak .
If I ... If I had a steak ,
I would fuck it .
You don 't like me cookin ' ?
Ugh , don 't be such an old bitch !
You 're drunk !
Ye don 't know what ye 're talkin ' ...
How could I possibly like
the horse shit you fix us for supper ?
Ye 're drunk , or ye wouldn 't be saying that !
Them tin kitchen shanty cooks
gave us fried donuts three times a day
and country ham bigger than your fist ...
Ye 're drunk ! Ye 're drunk ! Ye 're drunk !
- I 'm drunk ? - You heard me !
- You 've been drunk since ... - Damn ye !
Drunk since I first laid eyes on you .
Ye 're fond of me lobster , ain 't ye ?
You 're drunker than a Virginy fence .
I seen it . Ye 're fond of me lobster .
Say it .
Say it !
I don 't have to say nothin ' .
Damn ye !
Let Neptune strike ye dead , Winslow !
- [ shouts ] Hark ! - [ thunder cracks ]
Hark , Triton , Hark !
Bellow , bid our father , the sea king ,
rise from the depths , full foul in his fury ,
black waves teeming with salt-foam ,
to smother this young mouth with pungent slime ,
to choke ye , engorging yer organs
till ye turn blue and bloated
with bilge and brine and can scream no more .
Only when he , crowned in cockle shells
with slithering tentacled tail and steaming beard ,
take up his fell , be-finned arm ,
his coral-tined trident screeches
banshee-like in the tempest
and plunges right through yer gullet ,
bursting ye ,
a bulging bladder no more ,
but a blasted bloody film now ,
a nothing for the Harpies and the souls of dead sailors
to peck and claw and feed upon ,
only to be lapped up and swallowed
by the infinite waters
of the dread emperor himself ,
forgotten to any man ,
to any time ,
forgotten to any God or devil , forgotten even to the sea ,
for any stuff or part of Winslow ,
even any scantling of your soul ,
is Winslow no more ,
but is now itself the sea .
All right . Have it your way .
I like your cooking .
- [ thunder rumbling ] - [ clock ticking ]
[ clock continues ticking ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ grunting ]
Bitch .
[ wind howling outside ]
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ snoring ]
- [ creaks ] - [ Thomas snorts ]
[ Thomas ] Queer way to wear yer shoes .
Just didn 't wanna wake you , is all .
It 's a long night .
And such .
Hmm . The sun is over the yardarm .
Best find me some winks
afore the day draws farther on .
[ Thomas farts ]
Get back to yer duties
or I 'll give you a real keelhauling .
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ sighs ]
You ain 't even human no more .
Workin ' apart from folks so long .
You 're only tolerable when you 're drunk .
Get to work , says I !
To work !
[ mumbling indistinctly ]
[ machinery whirring ]
[ grunts ]
[ screaming ]
[ groans ]
[ gasping ]
[ grunting ]
[ bird squawks ]
[ both ] ♪ ... sassy little whore , hurrah ♪
♪ Me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me boy Doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls Doodle let me go ! ♪
♪ I took her in , I gave her gin And danced her on the floor ! ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me boy Doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls Doodle let me go ! ♪
[ vocalizing ]
Dance !
Dance , Winslow ! Dance !
[ Thomas continues dancing ]
[ grunts ]
♪ Come all you boys who wish to hear ♪
♪ How we got up to the woods last year ♪
♪ Into the sleigh we jacked our boots ♪
♪ Our teamster pointed to the big blue spruce ♪
♪ Timmy-ran-tin-ah Falla-doo-a-dah ♪
♪ Rant-and-roar and drunk-on-the-way ! ♪
[ distant foghorn ]
[ Thomas humming ]
♪ If but the birds were gin ♪
♪ If but the sun were a hearty reveler ♪
♪ I might give someone else me liver ♪
♪ On a Monday morning ♪
♪ My lover , she lies asleep ♪
♪ My lover is warm ♪
♪ And her heart is mellow ♪
♪ I would give the whole world ♪
♪ Just to share her pillow ♪
♪ On a Monday morning ... ♪ ♪
[ Thomas laughs ] Aye .
[ groans ]
[ both grunting ]
[ Ephraim ] Get off me ! Get off me !
- Thomas . - Aye .
- It 's Thomas . - Aye .
No , I ... I 'm Thomas .
I 'm Thomas . You 're Ephraim .
I lied .
Well , I 'll be scuppered .
I 'm Thomas . Tommy .
Tommy ? [ chuckling ] Tommy Winslow .
No . Tom Howard .
What 's Winslow ?
- It 's nothing . - Nothing ?
[ distant foghorn ]
Can I trust you ?
Don 't be spilling any of yer beans to me .
I ain 't interested .
No . It wasn 't that way , is all ...
I see what you 're fixin ' to do .
Git me all liquored up ...
Ye 're guilty conscience is ever as tiresome-borin '
as any a guilty conscience .
Worse . Worse .
It was ... It was a drive , see ...
It was ... It was a log drive , and he 's raggin ' on me .
No ... I see what you 're doing .
Nothing .
Look , Tom ...
Don 't be working to twist words out of my head .
I ain 't .
Um , I can 't ... I can 't do it .
Shut up yer own rag box .
I trust ... I trust ... I trust you .
No .
I ... I trust you , Tom .
You trust me ?
No , I don 't trust you at all .
[ laughing ]
[ Thomas coughing ]
[ distant foghorn ]
[ clock ticking ]
[ thunder rumbling ]
[ Ephraim ] And I had ' im handy and helpless .
Alone .
Too far downstream .
And I ... I wanted to do ' im in .
I admit I did .
Seein ' the back of his head .
One swipe of the cant hook 'd be all .
Uh ... It was ...
I ... I didn 't ...
I didn 't ... I did not .
The day was long as hell on that drive .
I was lead-tired . I admit it .
But I saw him slippin ' , not me .
We saw the jam comin ' .
I stood and he slipped .
He shouted up . And I ... I just stood there .
" Tom , you dog ! "
I just stood there , is all . Just ...
Just stood and watched ' im git swallowed by them logs .
And all I could think when he was done was ,
" I ... I could use me a smoke . "
That 's it .
So , I packed up his kit and fixins ,
as if they was my own and ...
Ephraim Winslow , well , now , he got a spiffy clean slate .
And Thomas Howard ,
well , he don 't .
No prospects .
How else am I gonna find respectable work ?
Tom !
[ Thomas echoing ] Why 'd y 'spill yer beans , Tommy ?
Why 'd y 'spill yer beans ?
[ foghorn blasting ]
[ panting ]
[ grunts ]
Don 't leave me !
- [ foghorn blasting ] - [ Thomas grunting ]
[ panting heavily ]
[ Thomas yells ]
[ yelling ]
[ continues yelling ]
You crazy son-of-a-bitch !
You smashed up the life boat !
Ye 're abandoning yer post !
- [ grunts ] - [ shatters ]
[ thunder rumbling ]
[ Ephraim ] What 're you gonna do ?
Send for the lighthouse establishment ?
Certain , says I !
I 'll report ye , I 'll bring the inspector up ...
I 'll report you ! I know what you done !
Who 's reportin ' who ? Ephraim Winslow ?
Or Thomas Howard ?
I know what you done .
You killed your second .
[ laughs ]
Your one-eyed junior man .
I found him .
In the lobster pot .
Said he went mad ?
You made him mad with that charm !
That scrimshaw trinket .
But I broke it , see .
See ?
Now I 'm free .
I 'm free from your designs !
[ laughing hysterically ]
And I got it all figured out ,
' cept what 's the secret mischief your keepin ' ...
Up there !
Jesus , Mary and Joseph , Tommy .
Last night you made a confession
' twould make a saint swear .
I don 't have nothin ' to confess ,
but you , spillin ' yer beans ,
look what it 's done to ye .
It 's made ye mad !
And I knew ye was mad
when y 'smashed up that life boat just now ,
a-chasing me with an axe , tryin ' to kill Ol ' Tom .
Don 't ye trust me , Tommy ?
Better hand me the dinner knife ye pocketed .
Y 'aint safe with it .
That 's a good lad .
Them 's government property .
Deducted from yer pay .
Look at yer shiverin ' .
Ye 're so mad , y 'know not up from down .
How long have we been on this rock ?
Five weeks ?
Two days ?
Where are we ?
Help me to recollect , who are you again , Tommy ?
I 'm probably a figment of your imagination .
This rock is a figment of yer imagination , too .
Ye 're probably wand 'rin ' through a grove of tag alders ,
up north in Canady ,
like a frostbitten maniac talkin ' to yerself ,
knee-deep in snow .
[ wind howling ]
[ grunts ]
I could use me a smoke .
We 're outta drink .
[ sputters and gags ]
Ooh !
Monkey pump !
[ both howling ]
[ machinery whirring ]
[ both laughing ]
[ thunder crashing ]
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ Ephraim ] This place is a sty .
[ Thomas ] Mornin ' to you too .
[ grunts ]
I wish I could go for a walk .
Be my guest .
You 'll get drowned .
[ clattering ]
[ coughing ]
[ clock ticking ]
[ grunts ]
[ clock continues ticking ]
Fiery pit !
[ grunts ]
Ain 't there no justice left in this world ?
[ match strikes ]
Thankee .
What 's wrong with yer hand ?
The other one .
Ye hear o ' tetanus ?
- Tet-a-nus ? - Yeah .
It started as a sliver of a cut , is all ...
I said I heard of it .
... from the forestaysail when we shoved off ...
- Don 't you ever shut up ? - ... but come a fortnight ,
- the bosun was a-shakin ' . - Stop .
His jaw locked tighter than an anchor ...
Shut your gum , goddamn it ! I can 't hear no more !
What were it ye accused me of ?
Y 'already told me y 'had me figgerd .
I 'm tired of your damned-fool yarns
and your Cap 'n Ahab horseshit .
You sound like a goddamned parody .
Givin ' and nagging orders like a spinster schoolmarm ,
and all the while turning this station
- to the Devil 's own rum hole . - Ye 're makin ' a fool of yerself .
Well , it 's all horseshit ,
your leg , and your sea life ,
all of it !
And if I hear one more word of horseshit
coming out of your foul , rotten tooth ,
- smelly old mouth ... - Ye ...
Shut up your gum , goddamn it !
I ain 't finished yet !
You think you 're so goddamned high and mighty
just ' cause you 're a goddamned lighthouse keeper ?
Well , you ain 't a captain of no ship and you never was !
You ain 't no general , you ain 't no copper ,
you ain 't the president , and you ain 't my father !
And I 'm sick of you actin ' like you is !
I 'm sick of your laughing , your snoring ,
and your goddamned farts .
Your goddamned ...
- Goddamn your farts ! - [ clattering ]
[ exhales ] You smell like piss ,
you smell like jism ,
like rotten dick , like curdled foreskin ,
like hot onions fucked a farmyard shit-house .
And I 'm sick of your smell . I 'm sick of it !
I 'm sick of it , you goddamned drunk .
You goddamned , no-account , son-of-a-bitch-bastard liar !
That 's what you are !
You 're a goddamned , drunken , horse-shitting ,
short , shit liar .
A liar !
[ panting ]
Ye have a way with words , Tommy .
[ groans in frustration ] Damn you !
Ye 're relieved of yer duties .
[ laughing hysterically ]
No need to tell me , old timer .
[ water sloshing ]
[ footsteps thudding ]
" Assistant slept late . "
" Work below standard . "
" Attitude hostile . "
" Assistant missing . "
" Given to habitual self-abuse in the supply shed . "
" Drunk on duty ! "
" Assault ! "
" Theft ! "
" Recommend severance without pay . "
- Severance without pay ? - [ book clatters ]
You trying to ruin me ?
I 'm a hard worker .
I am . I work as hard as any man .
- Ye lie , Thomas . - Stop it !
Ye lie to yerself , but y 'ain 't have the sauce to see it .
Please ...
Just let me into the light , old man .
I 've learned so much from you .
Just let me show you . Another chance .
Forgive and forget , I says .
Just let me into that lantern , is all .
Don 't make me beg ...
Or I 'll beg .
I 'll beg if that 's what you want . I 'll beg .
Please !
Please ! Please ! Please !
Stand down .
You selfish bastard !
Keepin ' it all to yourself .
You left your old lady ,
your children , for what ? For what ?
Look at ye , handsome lad , with eyes bright as a lady .
Come to this rock playin ' the tough .
Ye make me laugh with yer false grum .
Ye pretended to some mystery in yer quietudes ,
but there ain 't no mystery .
Ye 're an open book .
A picture , says I.
A painted actress screaming in the footlights ,
a bitch what wants to be coveted
for nothin ' but being born ,
cryin ' bout the silver spoon what should 've been yers .
Now look at ye cryin ' .
Boo ! Boo !
What you gonna do ?
Will ye kill me ?
Will ye ?
Will y 'kill me like y 'done that gull ?
- I didn 't ... - Liar !
Y 'murdering dog !
Twas ye what changed the wind on us .
Twas ye what damned us , dog . Twas ye !
Will y 'do what y 'wish y 'done to Ol ' Winslow ?
Will ye best me then ? For Winslow were right !
Thomas , ye 're a dog !
A filthy dog ! A dog !
[ both grunting ]
[ Thomas screaming ]
[ clattering ]
[ panting ]
[ Thomas laughing hysterically ]
[ creature chittering ]
[ grunting ]
[ Thomas ] Ye 're killing me !
[ panting ]
[ Thomas groaning softly ]
[ grunts ]
Bark .
Bark , boy .
Bark , laddy .
Bark .
[ Thomas ] Woof .
Ain 't ye never been to sea before ?
Bark , I says . Bark !
[ Thomas ] Ruff ! Ruff ! Ruff !
Bark , laddy !
Ruff ! Ruff ! Ruff !
- Now , there 's a good boy . - Ruff !
There 's a good dog .
Ruff ! Ruff ! Ruff !
Ruff !
Now roll over .
- [ waves crashing ] - [ seagulls squawking ]
Come on .
- [ groaning ] - Come on .
- [ Thomas groaning ] - Git !
[ Ephraim ] Get up here .
[ grunting ]
Good boy . Good boy .
Now you git in there , where you belong .
You do as I say , dog .
There 's my good lad .
[ Thomas groaning ]
[ Thomas ] Ye wish to see what 's in the lantern ?
So did me last assistant .
Shut up , old dog !
Polish your brasswork .
[ groans ]
O what Protean forms swim up from men 's minds ,
and melt in hot Promethean plunder ,
scorching eyes ,
with divine shames and horror ...
And casting them down to Davy Jones .
The others , still blind ,
yet in it see
all the divine graces
and to Fiddler 's Green sent ,
where no man is suffered to want or toil ,
but is ...
Ancient ...
Mutable and unchanging
as the she who girdles ' round the globe .
Them 's truth .
You 'll be punished .
[ seagulls squawking ]
[ panting ]
[ grunting ]
[ keys jangling ]
The light belongs to me !
[ groans ]
[ squelching ]
[ panting ]
[ sighs ]
Should pale death with treble dread
make the ocean caves our bed ,
God who hear 'st the surges roll ,
deign to save the suppliant soul .
[ exhales ]
[ crackling noises ]
[ inaudible ]
[ distorted laughter ]
[ distorted screaming ]
[ grunting ]
[ grunting stops ]
[ chains clinking softly ]
[ waves crashing ]
[ seagulls screeching ]
[ groaning softly ]
[ seagulls continue screeching ]
♪ It 's of a merchant 's daughter brought up in Callao ♪
♪ Hurrah me yaller girls doodle let me go ♪
♪ She took me in the parlour and said ♪
♪ Won 't you be my boy ? ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Oh all around the sofa , lads , and wasn 't it a go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ And about the hour of twelve o 'clock her own man he came home ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ As I was out a-walking down by the riverside ♪
♪ It was e 'er I seen this pretty girl a-swimming in the tide ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ As I was out a-walking all in the bright moonlight ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ It was e 'er I seen this girl a-swimming and arise , it shone so bright ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ I wish I was in Madame Gashay 's down in Callao ♪
♪ Where the girls hold on your bobstay and they never let it go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ We 'll cast a line ' round Madame Gashay 's and take the house in tow ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ We 'll tow it back to Liverpool all the way from Callao ♪
♪ Doodle let me go , me girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪
♪ Hurrah , me yaller girls , doodle let me go ♪ ♪